这一节，我们继续讨论离散概率的应用
In this segment, we're gonna continue with
a few more tools from discrete
再提醒一下，如果想了解这方面更多
probability, and I want to remind everyone
that if you wanna read more about this,
请参考维基百科的这个链接
there's more information in wiki books
article that is linked over here. So first
我们先回顾一下相关知识
我们说离散概率总是
let's do a quick recap of where we are. We
said that the discrete probability is
定义在有限集上的，这个集合我们记为U
always defined over a finite set, which
we're gonna denote by U, and typically for
典型的，U是全体N位二进制字符串的集合
us, U is going to be the set of all N bit
binary strings, which we denote by zero
我们记为｛0,1｝^N。现在U上的概率分布P
one to N. Now a probability distribution P
over this universe U is basically a
为全局U中的每个元素赋予权重
function that assigns to every element in
the universe a weight in the interval zero
权重从0到1，如果我们把各元素的权重加起来
to one, such that if we sum the weight of
all these elements, the sum basically sums
答案是1.我们把全局的子集称为事件
up to one. Now we have said that subset of
the universe is what called an event, and
我们说事件的概率是其所有元素的权重和
we said that probability of an event is
basically the sum of all the weights of
我们还说事件的概率是某个实数
all the elements in the event and we said
that probability of an event is some real
介于0和1之间。我还要提醒大家
numbers in the interval zero to one. And I
would remind everyone the basically
整个全局的概率是1，事实上
probability of the entire universe is
basically the one by the fact that sum of
所有权重加一块是1
然后我们定义了随机变量是什么
all the weights sums up to one. Then we
define what a random variable is. Formally,
形式上，随机变量是一个从全局
到其他集合的函数
a random variable is a, is a function from
the universe of some other sets. But the
我希望大家记住随机变量从
thing that I want you to remember is that
the random variable takes, values in some
某集合v中取值。事实上随机变量定义了
集合v上的概率分布
set v And, in fact, the random variable
defines the distribution on this set v. So
下一个我们需要的概念是独立性
我将简单定义一下这个概念
the next concept we need is what's called
independence. And I'm gonna very briefly
如果你想了解更多关于独立性的知识
define this. If you want to read more about
independence, please go ahead and look at
去读维基百科的文章吧。本质上
我们说事件A和B互相独立
the wiki books article. But essentially we
say that two events A and B are
当你知道事件A发生的话
independent of one another if When you
know that event A happens, that tells you
这并没有告诉你事件B有没有发生。形式化地
nothing about whether event B actually
happened or not. Formally, the way we
我们这样定义独立性
A和B的概率，或者说
define independence is to say that, the
probability of A and B, namely, that both
两事件同时发生的概率等于
事件A的概率乘以B的概率
events happened, is actually=to the
probability of event A the probability of
所以用乘法来表示概率的联结
event B. So multiplication, in some sense,
the fact that probabilities multiply under
反映了事件的独立性。我说过
conjunction, captures the fact that these
events are independent. And as I said, if
如果你想了解更多，请看看相关材料
you wanna read more about that, please
take a look at the background material.
现在同样的道理可以应用在随机变量上
Now the same thing can be said for random
variables. So suppose we have two random
设有两随机变量x和y。它们从集合v中取值
variables x and y. They take values in
some set v. Then we say that these random
我们说这些随机变量相互独立
如果概率P(x=a,y=b)
variables are independent if the
probability that x = a, and y = b is equal
等于两概率乘积P(x=a)P(y=b)
这意味着，即使你知道x=a
to the product of these two probabilities.
Basically what this means is, even if you
你也一点不知道y的值。好的
know that x = a, that tells you nothing
about the value of y. Okay, that, that's
这就是乘法的意义
这个随机变量的乘法
what this multiplication means. And again
this needs to hold for all A and B in the
对空间中所有a和b恒成立
那么，又要运用大家的记忆力了
space of values of these random variables
So, just again to job your memory. If
大家之前是否见过这个例子？
you've seen this before, a very quick
example. Suppose we look at the, set of,
我们看2位字符串的集合，即00，01，10，11
of two bit strings. So, zero, zero, zero,
one, one zero and, one, one. And suppose we
我们从中随机选择。好，我们
从这四个元素中随机选一个
choose a random, from this set. Okay so we
randomly choose one of these four elements
以均匀的概率。现在我们定义两个随机变量
with equal probability. Now let's define
two random variables. X is gonna be the
X是选中字符串的最低位，Y则是最高位
least significant bit that was generated,
and Y is gonna be the most significant bit
我声称，随机变量X和Y是相互独立的
generated. So I claim that, these random
variables, x and y, are independent of one
直观地看，随机均匀地选择r
another. And the way to see that
intuitively, is to realize that choosing r
四选一基本上跟抛掷硬币一致
uniformly, from the set of four elements
is basically the same as flipping a coin
抛掷均匀硬币两次。第一位对应
第一次抛掷结果
An unbiased coin twice. The first bit
corresponds to the outcome of the first
第二位对应第二次抛掷结果
flip and the second bit corresponds to the
outcome of the second flip. And of course
当然共有四种结果。四种结果等可能出现
there are four possible outcomes. All four
outcomes are equally likely which is why
这也是为什么我们取2位字符串上的均匀分布
现在我们看X和Y的独立性
we get the uniform distributions over two
bit strings. Now our variables X and Y. Y
如果我们告诉大家第一次抛掷结果
the independents. Basically if I tell you
result of the first flip namely I tell you
也就是R的最低位。那么我告诉大家
the least signify bit of R. So I tell you
how the first coin you know whether it
第一次抛出正面还是背面
你是无法得知第二次的结果的
fell on its head or fell on its tails.
That tells you nothing about the result of
直观地，你可能觉得这些随机变量
the second flip. Which is why intuitively,
you might, you might expect these random
是相互独立的。但形式上讲
variables to be independent of one
another. But formally, we would have to
我们需要证明之，对所以0，1配对成立
x=0,y=0；x=1,y=1等等
prove that, for, all 01 pairs, the
probability of, x=0 and y=0, x=1, y=1, and
这些概率是满足乘法性质的
我们做一个配对为例
so on. These probabilities multiply. Let's
just do it for one of these pairs. So
我们看x=0,y=0的概率
let's look at the probability that x is =
to zero, and y is = to zero. Well, you see
x=0,y=0的概率就是
that the probability that x is equal to
zero and y is equal to zero is basically
随机变量r=(0,0)的概率
那r=(0,0)的概率是多少？
the probability that r is equal to zero,
zero. And what's the probability that r is
根据均匀分布，这个概率等于1/4
equal to zero, zero? Well, by the uniform
distribution, that's basically equal to
也就是1除以全局大小，这里是1/4
one-fourth. What it's one over size of the
set which is one fourth in this case. And
注意这些概率满足乘法性质
well low and behold that's in fact these
provabilities multiply. Because
X等于0的概率
again the probability that X is equal to
zero. The probability that least significant
R的最低位等于0的概率
这个概率严格等于1/2
bit of R is equal to zero. This
probability is exactly one half because
因为只有两个元素的最低位是0
there is exactly two elements that have
their, least significant bit equals to zero.
四选二的概率是1/2，类似地
Two out of four elements gives you a
probability of one half. And similarly the
Y等于0的概率也是1/2
所以实际上概率满足乘法
probability that Y is equal to zero is
also one half so in fact the probability
好的，这就是独立的概念
我之所以想告诉大家这个
multiplies. Okay, so that's, this concept
of independence And the reason I wanted to
是因为我们要看一个异或的重要性质
show you that is because we're gonna look
at an, an important property of XOR that
这个性质我们将反复用到
在讨论异或之前，我们简单回顾一下
we're gonna use again and again. So before
we talk about XOR, let me just do a very
异或是什么。当然
异或就是两位的和
quick review of what XOR is. So, of
course, XOR of two bits means the addition
并取模2。为保证大家都能明白
of those bits, modular two. So just a
kind of, make sure everybody's on the same
如果我们有两位，00，01，10，11
它们的异或的真值表
page. If we have two bits, so 00, 01, ten and
eleven. Their XOR or the truth table of
就是的模2和。可以看到，1+1=2
the XOR is basically just the addition
modular two. As you can see, one+1 is= to
模2后得0。所以这就是异或的真值表
two, modular two. That's=to zero. So this
is the truth table for an XOR. And
我总是使用圈和里面的加号来表示异或
I'm always going to denote XOR by the
circle with a + inside. And then when I
当我想应用异或操作时，我逐位使用模2加法
wanna apply XOR to bit strings, I apply
the, addition modular two operation,
例如，这两个字符串的异或是110
bitwise. So, for example, the XOR of these
two strings would be, 110, and I guess
大家补完剩余的异或结果
确保大家明白了
I'll let you fill out the rest of the
XORs, just to make sure we're all on the
当然结果是1101
same page. So of course is comes out to
one, one zero one. Now, we're gonna be
本课程需要做大量的异或
事实上有一个经典的笑话
doing a lot of XORing in this class. In
fact, there's a classical joke that the
密码学家只会玩异或
only think cryptographers know how to do
is just XOR things together. But I want to
我想解释一下为什么密码学里异或如此常见
explain to you why we see XOR so
frequently in cryptography. Basically, XOR
异或具有如下重要性质
has a very important property, and the
property is the following. Suppose we have
假设我们有随机变量y
随机分布于｛0，1｝^n
a random variable y. That's distributed
arbitrarily over 01 to the n. So we know
我们不知道y的概率分布
假设我们有另一独立的随机变量x
nothing about the distribution of y. But
now, suppose we have an independent random
在｛0，1｝^n上均匀分布
variable that happens to be uniformly
distributed also over 01 to the n. So it's
x是均匀分布很重要，而且x与y独立
very important that x is uniform and is
independent of y. So now let's define the
我们定义随机变量为x和y的异或
然后我宣称
random variable which is the XOR of x and
y. Then I claim that no matter what
无论y如何分布，z总是均匀分布的随机变量
distribution y started with, this z is
always going to be a uniform, random
换句话说，如果我取一含恶意的分布
variable. So in other words if I take an
arbitrarily malicious distribution and I
然后我用一个均匀分布的随机变量异或它
结果得到的是均匀分布的随机变量
XOR with independent uniform random
variable what I end up with is a uniform
这又是一个重要性质
random variable. Okay and this again is
kind of a key property that makes XOR
使得异或在密码中非常有用。这一点
其实非常容易证明
very useful for crypto. So this is
actually a very simple factor to prove,
我们直接证明之。我先证n=1的情况
let's just go ahead and do it, let's just
prove it for one bit so for n = one. Okay,
我们写出各个随机变量的概率分布
so the way we'll do it is we'll basically
write out the probability distributions
对应随机变量y
for the various random variables. So let's
see, for the random variable y. Well, the
这个随机变量可以是0或1
我们设它等于0的概率是P0
random variable can be either zero or one.
And let's say that P0 is the probability
等于1的概率是P1
that it's = to zero, and P1 is the
probability that it's =to one. Okay, so
这时我们的一个表。类似地
对随机变量x我们也有一个表
that's one of our tables. Similarly, we're
gonna have a table for the variable x.
x的分布更为简单，它是均匀分布
Well, the variable x is much easier.
That's a uniform random variable. So the
所以x等于0的概率是1/2
probability that it's=to zero is exactly
one half The probability that's it's=to
等于1的概率也是1/2
现在我们写出联合分布的概率
one is also exactly one half. Now, let's
write out the probabilities for the join
换句话说，我们要看y和x的组合的概率
distribution. In, in other words, let's
see what the probability, is for the
比如说，y=0且x=0的可能性有多大
various, joint values of y and x. In other
words, how likely is, it that y is zero,
y=0且x=1，y=1且x=0，还有(1,1)
and x is zero. Y is zero, and x is one. Y
is one and x is zero, and eleven. Well, so
因为我们假设变量之间相互独立
what we do is, basically, because we
assume the variables are independent, all
我们只要算概率乘积即可
we have to do is multiply the
probabilities. So The probability that y
那么y=0的概率是P0
x=0的概率是1/2
is equal to zero is p zero. Probability
that x is equal to zero is one-half. So
所以00的概率就是P0/2，类似地
the proximity that, we get 00 as exactly p
zero over two. Similarly for zero one
(0,1)是P0/2，(1,0)是P1/2
we'll get p zero over two, for one zero
we'll get p one over two. And for 1-1,
(1,1)，也就是y=1，且x=1
again, the probability that y is=to one,
and x is=to one, Well, that's P1  the
其概率是P1/2，对吧？
probability that x is=to one, which is a
half, so it's P1 over two. Okay? So those
所以那些是x和y的四种情况的概率
are the four, probabilities for the
various options for x and y. So now, let's
我们来分析，z等于0的概率是多少？
analyze, what is the probability that z is
equal to zero? Well, the probability that
z等于0的概率等于。。我们这样写
z is=to zero is basically the same as the
probability that, let's write it this way,
(x,y)=(0,0)或(1,1)的概率
那些是z为0的两种可能情况
xy. Is=to 00. Or xy is=to, eleven. Those
are the two possible cases that z is=to
因为z是x和y的异或
由于这些事件是不相交的
zero. Because z is the XOR of x and y. Now,
these events are disjoint, so, this
这个表达式可以简单地写成上面两式的和
expression can simply be written as the
sum of the two expressions given above. So
即(x,y)=(0,0)的概率
加上(x,y)=(1,1)的概率
basically, it's the probability that xy
is=to 00, plus the probability that xy,
我们可以在表中找到这些概率
is=to eleven. So now we can simply look up
these probabilities in our table. So the
(x,y)=(0,0)的概率是P0/2
probability that xy is equal to 00 is
simply p zero over two, and the
(x,y)=(1,1)的概率是P1/2
probability that xy is equal to one, one
is simply p one over two. So we get P0
所以最后概率是(P0+P1)/2
P0和P1是什么？
over two +P1 over two. But what do we kn-,
what do we know about P0 and P1? Well,
它们是一个概率分布，所以P0+P1=1
it's a probability distribution.
Therefore, P0+P1 must =one. And therefore,
因此分式为1/2。因为P0+P1=1
this fraction here must= to a half. P0+P1
is =to one. So therefore, the sum of these
所以两者的和为1/2。结束了
我们已证完z=0的情况
two terms must = a half. And we're done.
Basically, we proved that the probability
是1/2，因此z=1的概率也是1/2
that z is = to zero. Is one half,
therefore the probability that z is equal
所以z是一均匀分布的随机变量
to one is also one half. Therefore z is a
uniform random variable. So the simple
这个简单定理是XOR如此实用的主要原因
theorem is the main reason why XOR is so
useful in cartography. The last thing I
关于离散概率我们最后想说的是生日悖论
wanna show you about discrete probability
is what's called the birthday paradox. And
我这里简单说一下，因为后面我们还会看到它
I'm gonna do it really fast here because
we're gonna come back later on, and talk
并会更详细地介绍之。生日悖论是说
about this in more detail. So, the
birthday paradox says the following
我从全局U中选择n个随机变量
suppose I choose n random variables in our
universe u. Okay. And it just so happens
这些随机变量是相互独立的
that these variables are independent of
one another. They actually don't have to
它们不一定是均匀分布的
我们只需假定它们同分布
be uniform. All we need to assume is that
they're distributed in the same way. The
最重要的是它们相互独立
most important property though is that
they're independent of one another. So the
定理说如果取约U的大小的平方根个元素
theorem says that if you choose roughly
the square root of the size of u elements,
我们可以忽略这个1.2，这不重要
we're kind of ignoring this 1.2 here, it
doesn't really matter. But if you choose
但是如果你选择了U的大小的平方根个元素
square root of the size of u elements,
then basically there's a good chance that
你选了两个相同元素的可能性很大
换句话说，如果你取样|U|的平方根次
there are two elements that are the same.
In other words, if you sample about square
很可能你的两次取样是相等的
root a few times, then it's likely that
two of your samples will be
这个倒着的E表示存在，提醒一下大家
equal to one another. And by the way, I
should point out that this inverted E,
所以存在i和j满足R(i)=R(j)
just means exists. So there exist the
I and j such that r I is equal
这是个具体的例子，我们还会见很多次
to r j. So here's a concrete example.
We'll actually see many, many times.
设想我们的全局为全体128位字符串
Suppose our universe consist of all
strings of length of one hundred and
那么U的大小很大，为2的128次方
twenty eight bits. So the size of U is
gigantic it's actually two to the hundred
它是一个很大很大的集合
但是如果你取样2的64次方次
and twenty eight. It's a very, very large
set. But it so happens if you sample say
也就是U大小的平方根
around two the sixty four times from the
set. This is about the square root of U
很有可能你的两次取样是同样的信息
then is very likely that two of your
sample messages will actually be the same.
为什么这叫悖论呢？
以前这个是在描述人们生日的时候说的
So why is, this called the paradox? Well,
traditionally it's described in terms of
把这些取样视为某人的生日
people's birthdays. So you would think
that each of these samples would be
问题就是：需要多少人
someone's birthday. And so the question is
how many people need to get together so
使得有两人的生日相同？
that there are two people that have the
same birthday? So, just as a simple
简单算一下，一年365天
calculation you can see there are 365 days in
the year, so you would need about 1.2
需要1.2倍的365的平方根
times the square root of 365 people until
the probability that two of them have the
这样有两人有相同生日的概率多于1/2
如果我没算错，是24人
same birthday is more than a half. This if
I'm not mistaken is about 24, which means
意味着如果随机挑24人，集中在一个房间里
那么非常有可能有两人的生日
that if 24 random people get together in a
room it's very likely that two of them
是相同的。这就是为什么叫悖论
will actually have the same birthday. This
is why it's called a paradox, because 24
因为24被认为是比人预期低得多
supposedly is a smaller number than you
would expect. Interestingly, people's
(这并不是逻辑上的悖论)
有趣的是，人们的生日并不是365天均匀分布的
birthdays are not actually uniform across
all 365 days of the year. There's actually
实际上有偏向于⑨月
不过我想这与我们的讨论无关
a bias towards September. But, I guess
that's not, that's not relative to the
我最后想更具体地展示一下生日悖论
discussion here. The last thing I
wanted to do is just show you the birthday
假设全局有一百万的样本
paradox a bit more concretely. So, suppose
we have a universe of about a million
如果我们取样约1200次
samples, then you can see that when we
sample roughly 1200 times, the probability
我们两次取到同样数的概率约为1/2
that we get, we sample the same number,
the same element twice is roughly half. But
不过，两次取样相同的概率
the probability of sampling the same
number twice actually converges very
很快收敛于1。如果我们取样2200次
quickly to one. You can see that if we
about 2200 items, then the probability
两次取样相同的概率已是90%了
that two of those items are the same,
already is 90 percent and You know, 3000
3000次的时候基本上就是1了
所以是很快地收敛到1的
then it's basically one. So this
conversion is very quickly to one as soon
只要取样次数超过全局大小的平方根次
as he goes beyond the square root of the
size of the universe. So we're gonna come
后面我们还会来看生日悖论的更多细节
back and study the birthday paradox in
more detail later on, but I just for now,
我现在只想让大家知道生日悖论是什么
那么我们结束本节
wanted you to know what it is. So that's
the end of this segment, and then in the
下一节开始第一个加密系统
next segment we'll start with our first
example of encryption systems.
【ikamusume酱 译注】